Inventory of the Gerard William Kelley papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Gerard William Kelley papers
1942-1955
70009
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope, 1 album box (1.3 linear feet)
Correspondence, diary, orders, memoranda, and photographs relating to American military operations on Saipan, the Marianas, Makin Atoll, and elsewhere in the Pacific Theater during World War II.
Kelley, Gerard William, 1903-1969.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1970.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Brigadier general, United States Army; commanding officer, 165th Infantry Regiment, 1943-1945.
Scope and Content of Collection
Collection includes correspondence, diary, orders, memoranda, and photographs relating to American military operations on Saipan, the Marianas, Makin Atoll, and elsewhere in the Pacific Theater during World War II.
United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 165th.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Pacific Ocean.
- 165th Infantry File, 1942-1945
  - Orders, special orders, memorandum, and other materials regarding information covering the island of Hawaii. Headquarters, Hawaiian Department, Office of the Department of Engineer, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Correspondence, Headquarters 165th Infantry, APO 27, San Francisco, California, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Record of Operation FORAGER, unit journal, 1944 January 16 - August 16 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- Controversial Publications, 1944-1955
  Scope and Contents note
  Regarding the battle of Saipan, concerning the 27th Division.
  - "Campaign in the Marianas" manuscript by Dr. Philip A. Crowl
    - Review of the manuscript by author (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Resume of Gerard Kelley's experience as a member of the review panel to discuss the manuscript, 1955 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Correspondence with extensive comments, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - General Smith's article
    Time magazine, 1944 September 18.
    - Gerard Kelley review of the article, 1944 Ocotober 21 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Refutation of article, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Secret special operations map, Saipan area, 1944 March (Box-folder 1: 9)
- Colonel Gerard W. Kelley File, 1942-1945
  - Diary, 1942 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Diary, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Notes and diary, Makin and Saipan, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Citation, to accompany General Orders, Headquarters, 165th Infantry, 1945 January 17 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Office correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 2: 2-4)
- Printed Matter, 1943-1946
  - "Saipan: Eyewitness Tells of Island Fight," by Robert Sherrod, magazine article, undated (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Clippings, 1943 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - The Capture of Makin (20 November-24 November 1943), Historical Division, War Department, Washington, D.C., 1946 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- Photographs, 1943
  - 21 prints depicting activities of the 165th Infantry in the Pacific area in World War II, 1943 (Envelope mA)
  - Album depicting the battle of Makin Atoll, Butaritari, and the Gilbert Islands fought by the 165th Infantry, 1943 November 20-23 (Album fB)